Corle mss., LMC 1246
Lilly Library
Corle mss.
1942-1965
Lilly Library
Corle, Edwin, 1906-1956.
LMC 1246
4 Boxes
The Corle mss., 1942-1965, consists of letters between author Edwin Corle, 1906-1965, and his publishers, series editors, and magazine editors in addition to writings including Corle's stories, essays, novels, non-fiction books, and extensive holograph and typescript drafts of a multi-volume novel, The Californians, left uncompleted upon his death.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1997.
Biographical Note
Author, Edwin Corle, 1906-1956, is known for his realistic portrayals of Native American life in the early 20th century. After a brief career writing for radio Corle began writing numerous short stories and non-fiction pieces for magazines. In 1934 his Mojave: A Book of Stories was published. This was followed a year later by his first and most successful novel Fig Tree John based on a Cahuilla Indian from southern California. In addition to other novels, Corle also wrote non-fiction, including books on the Grand Canyon and the Gila River. In the 1950s, Corle began what was to be his most important work, a multi-volume novel called The Californians. The work was left uncompleted upon his death.
Arrangement/Organization
Arranged into two series: Correspondence and Writings.
Scope and Content Note
Consists of letters between Corle and his publishers, series editors, and magazine editors and writings including Corle's stories, essays, novels, non-fiction books, and extensive holograph and typescript drafts of a multi-volume novel, The Californians, left uncompleted upon his death.
The majority of correspondence concerns Corle's writings in the 1950s: the technical aspects of the publishing of The Gila: River of the Southwest the ideas for the proposed multi-volume series of novels The Californians, as well as Corle's attempts to sell his ultimately unpublished work of popular science Space, Time, and Man. An early group of letters from the 1940s were written while Corle was in the military, and deal mostly with his assignments.
Authors, American--Correspondence; Indians of North America.; Correspondence; Letters; Radio authorship; Literature; Indians of North America--History--20th century; America--History--20th century; Intellectuals--Books and reading--America--History--20th century; Corle, Edwin, 1906-1956.; Corle, Edwin, 1906-1956 --Correspondence.; Corle, Edwin, 1906-1956. Californians.
- Correspondence, 1942-1965
  - 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, 1942-1965
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged in alphabetical order by title. Publishing information given where known.
  - Billy the Kid. New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce, (Novel), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - A Book of Clowns. (Book proposal) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burro Alley. New York: Random House, (Novel), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - California Today. (Non-fiction) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Central Park West. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Club Absolute. (Drama) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Coarse Gold. New York: Dutton, (Novel), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Death of a Dinosaur. (Non-fiction) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Devil's Highway. (Book proposal) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Duck. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Evening at Home. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition for Gentlemen. (Outline for story or novel) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fig Tree John. New York: Liveright, (Novel), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Fixer. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Front Page Headlines. (Drama) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Gift. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Gila, River of the Southwest. New York: Rinehart(Non-fiction), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24-27)
  - How I Became a Christmas Tree. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Inside Information. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - In Winter Light. New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce, (Novel), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30-32)
  - Kilometer 500. (Drama) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The King of Cambodia. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - A Law of Probability. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Marble Palace. (Story?) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Mr. Uxmier and Theophilus. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Nasty Ice Cream Man. (Story) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - No Man On Earth. (Story?) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Old Dogs. (Story?) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Palm of Your Hand. (Ideas for a novel) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - People on the Earth. New York: Random House, (Novel), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Perpetual Motion. (Ideas for a story or novel) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Picnic. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Plot and a Cigarette. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pro and Con. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Project for a book of short stories. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Project for a novel. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Red Velvet. (Story?) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Seeing California. (Essay?) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sexual Behavior in Shakespeare's "Othello". (Essay) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Solitaire. New York: Dutton, (Drama), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Space, Time and Man. (Non-fiction) (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
  - Speak of the Devil. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Terrible White Man. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - They're Having a Fiesta. (Story) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Three Ways To Mecca. New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce, (Novel), 1947 (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    Includes the script for The Man in the Dog Suit, a play in three acts, by Albert Beich and William H. Wright which was based on Three Ways To Mecca.
  - Tungsten Over Darwin. Atlantic Monthly 169 :642-644. (Essay), (May 1942) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Widow. Yale Review 39: 337-343. (Story), (December 1949) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Yesterday. (Ideas for a play) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Yuma. (Essay) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Californians. (Novel) (Box 2, Folder 30-37)
    General
    Begun as the first of a multi-volume series of historical fiction, the project was left unfinished upon Corle's death.
  - The Californians. (cont.) (Box 3-4)